立法會主席。
我諗要。
Q Q。
發現。
陳建波議員就獨立監察警方處理投訴委員會二零一二一三工作報告向本會發言，陳建波議員。
多謝，多謝主席。
我僅代表獨立監察警方處理投訴委員會，即係監警會，提交該會於二零零九年成為法定機構後嘅第四份工作報告。
呢份工作報告咧係涵蓋咗財政年度截至二零一三年三月三一日。
喺二零一二一三年，監警會審核同埋通過咗二千四百八十九宗投訴警察個案嘅調查結果。
涉及咧係四千八百八十四項嘅指控，比上一年度咧分別減少咗二十點九個percent同埋二十一點七個percent。
喺呢個財政年度獲得通過嘅指控中咧，佔最多嘅咧就係疏忽職守，有二千三百一十七項；行為不當或者態度欠佳、粗言餉語，有一千七百八十九項；同埋毆打，有三百二十三項。
呢三類嘅指控咧，係佔咗二零一二一三年度指控總值嘅總數嘅九十點七個percent。
喺二零一三一一二年度通過嘅指控中咧，需要展開全面調查嘅咧係有一千五百零七項，當中咧有一百零一行咧被列為獲證實屬實。
六十一項咧被列為未經舉報，但證實屬實；二十九項咧被列為無法完全證明屬實；六百三十項咧被列為咧係無法證實；八十一項咧被列為虛假不妥，同埋咧係六百零五項咧被列為咧係並無過錯嘅。上
嘅數字咧，包括咗一百六十六項經監警會提出質詢後咧，警方同意我哋嘅意見，並且更改最初調查結果嘅指控。
喺二零一二一三年，監警會就通過嘅個案咧，提出咗九百三十八項質詢或者建議，當中咧有四百六十八項咧係質詢或者建議係獲警方係接納嘅。
喺觀察員嘅計劃之下咧，喺二零一二一三年咧，共進行咗二千零十二次嘅觀察，比上一年度咧係減少咗零點四percent。喺報告期之內咧，係監警會共會見咗兩位人士，就調查嘅報告咧係澄清事宜嘅。
監警會除咗監察投訴警察科嘅投訴調查工作之外咧，並致力就公眾關注嘅議題咧，同警方同埋持份者咧係加強聯繫嘅，希望監警會可以作為雙方嘅橋樑，為彼此提供一個意見交流嘅平台。
促進咧係大家嘅瞭解。
主席，我僅代表獨立監察警方處理投訴委員會，藉住今次向本會提交報告嘅機會咧，係感謝本會同埋其他持份者對監警會工作嘅支持。主席，我緊接陳詞。
石禮謙議員就政府賬目委員會第六十A號報告書向本會發言。石禮謙議員。Thank you, Mr. President. On behalf of the Public Accounts Committee.
我有榮耀將我們的報告號碼68呈上。
This report is supplemental to the committee's report number 60, and contains our conclusions and recommendations on Chapter 7 of the report number 60 of the Director of Audits' report on preventive education and enlisting public support.
Against corruption.
主席，Before I report on the conclusions and recommendations made by the committee.
I, on behalf of the PAC, would like to point out that the committee recognises.
The dedication and the good work of the Independent Commission Against Corruption and its staff in making Hong Kong a world-renowned corrupt-free society during the last 40 years.
委員會的報告，今天表決。
only deals with the handling of official entertainment, duty visits outside Hong Kong, and gifts during the tenure of the former commissioner of ICAC, Mr Timothy Tong Him Ming, which I shall highlight below.
The committee deplores the inadequacies and non-compliances of the ICC in handling of the official entertainment, duty visits outside Hong Kong, and gifts during the tenure of the former commissioner of ICC, Mr Timothy Tong, and condemns.
懲罰當時ICAC為有損香港為人所知的聲譽，作為一個貪污的場所，以及ICAC作為反貪污先驅的聲譽。
第二， erosion the credibility of the ICAC and the community relations department of the ICAC in particular in educating the public and enlisting public support against corruption.
Thirdly, undermine the effectiveness of the work of the community relation department, as public funds, which should have been used to provide more organisations and persons with preventive education.
and at least greatest.
公共支持，對腐敗，被花在奢侈的官方娛樂和禮物，以及過度的公務訪問。
Now, I touch on the subject of public money being spent on the work of community relation department.
委員會表達。
alarm and strong resentment, and found that unacceptable that public money, which should have been used on providing preventive education and enlisting public support locally against corruption by the community relations department.
Have been spent by the ICAC on official entertainment, gift and duty visits outside Hong Kong during the tenure of the Commissioner of ICAC, Mr. Tong Hing Ming.
The committee considers it inexcusable and condemns the then ICAC for failing to put in place adequate checks and balances to ensure the handling of its official entertainment, gift and duty visit outside Hong Kong.
which was carried out in the most
which should have been carried out in the most appropriate, economical, effective and efficient manner during the tenure of the former ICAC.
Commissioner Mr Timothy Tong, I shall now elaborate further on the inadequacies and the non-compliances identified in these three matters. On the subject of official entertainment, on the handling of official entertainment, the committee notes that the Community Relation Department
Of ICAC had continued to exclude the cost of wine and hard liquor procured separately from the expenditure of the meal it organised.
Despite two incidents that took place in 2008 and 2009 respectively, first, the administrative the administration branch of the ICAC had introduced the ICAC Form 569.
在2008年6月，隨後因歐盟關係決定排除波爾多和馬圖伊，於一場由前ICAC委員會委員主持的晚宴中，
Timothy Tom on 18 September 2007.
The main purpose of the form, Mr. President, was to facilitate ICAC officers to comply with government guidelines on official entertainment. That is to include the cost of wine and hard liquor procured separately in the total expenditure of the mail for control.
第一，目的。第二，修訂案於2009年7月對ICAC委員會的常規命令就娛樂開支作出修訂。修訂命令明確指出，每人娛樂開支應包括飲食。
and tips.
on the subject of duty visit.
Regarding the handling of duty visits outside Hong Kong, the committee notes that whilst the commissioner of ICAC is required to seek approval from the chief executive for attending duty visits outside Hong Kong, the former ICAC commissioner, Mr. Timothy.
唐金明，make no confirmation with the receiving parties on the detailed itinerary prior to submitting the applications to the chief executive for approval.
This had allowed changes to duty visit plan, including, reportedly, adding sightseeing activities and visit more locations without the knowledge of the chief executive.
An example was the duty visit to Beijing and Yunnan in January 2009. Mr. Tong's application to the CE.
did not include the trip to Lijiang, which mainly involved visits to scenic spots.
on the subject of gift, on the handling of gift, the committee notes that it is the stated policy of ICAC since 1996 to limit to the minimum of exchange of gift on official occasions.
Where an exchange of gift is unavoidable, the exchange should be made from organisation to organisation. This policy was later incorporated into the ICAC Commission Standing Orders on acceptance of advantages.
委員會也註明，一些委員會範圍內由前ICAC委員長湯金明批准的禮物，例如牛肉燒腿和魚丸，不能説是委員會範圍內的禮物。
And some other commission-wide gifts, such as scarves and a camera, were of a personal nature and were expensive.
on on the subject of other matters, in addition.
On official entertainment, the committee also expressed grave dismay and finds it inexcusable that the community relations department had continued the practice of not including the cost of wine and hard liquor per crew separately in the total expenditure of.
The mail in blatant disregard to the relevant requirement.
在委員會常規議程，如我早前所説。
The committee expressed grave dismay and found it inexcusable that the administration branch of the ICAC then failed to serve as a gatekeeper for proper use of public money, as it had failed to ensure the requirements of the relevant Commission Standing Order.
And government rules and regulation were complied with.
As the public has high expectation of the conduct of the Commissioner of ICAC, the committee consider it inexcusable and condemn the former ICAC Commissioner, Mr. Tong Hing Ming.
for his ignorance or total disregard to the requirement to include the cost of wine and hard liquor produced separately in the expenditure of the meal, and the requirement that the giving of gifts should be to organisation as opposed to.
個別。
And should be kept to the minimum, and to avoid attracting criticism of soliciting gifts and giving rise to unnecessary exchanges of gifts.
The committee also expressed alarm and strong resentment and find it unacceptable that moutai was served and consumed at many of the official entertainment hosted.
或attend by the then Mr Timothy Tong during his tenure as Commissioner of ICAC.
not only has such serving of maltoid increased the cost of the meals.
Official businesses of the ICAC, which might and often be confidential in nature, could be divulged under the influence of hot liquor or alcohol. The committee considers that it is inappropriate for the ICAC, a law enforcement agency.
到服務馬爾代夫，做官方 entertain。
On the way forward, to prevent the recurrence of the inadequacies of the non-compliances identified in the report.
委員會敦促ICAC應首先，實行更多查核和制衡，以確保公帑用於最合適、經濟、經濟有效和高效的方式；其次，採取行動，以確保無。
Attempts will be made by ICAC officers to circumvent or violate the ICAC's regulatory system and procedure procedures for handling official entertainment, duty visits outside Hong Kong, and the giving of gifts to indulge the wishes and whims of their superiors.
regarding the work of the community relations department, the committee urges the department not to, in pursuit of making greater use of
The mass media and web platform to disseminate pro-PT messages, slacken its work on making face-to-face contact with different segments of the community and the general public to achieve the same, having regard to the fact that conducting activities by face-to-face approach.
Has been consistently acknowledged by ICAC as the most effective way to get the anti-corruption messages across.
最後ly。
先生，我 wish to record our appreciation of the contribution made by members.
Of the committee, our gratitude also goes to the witnesses who attended the hearing, helped by the committee.
And I will also like to express our gratitude to the director of audit and his colleague for their unfailing support. Lastly, but not the least, I like to thank the secretariat for giving us that unfailing support. Thank you, Mr. President.